[Music]
there are recommended daily intakes of
essential nutrients like vitamins to
prevent deficiencies but recently the
first dietary recommendation for a
bioactive food compound was published
bioactives are food compounds that are
not necessary for basic human needs but
may have health benefits for example
plant metabolites called flavonoids Flav
flavenoids are a type of polyphenol of
which the most commonly consumed are
flaven 3ol also known as just
flavonols a review of the literature
suggested that the intake of 400 to 600
milligrams a day of flavonol would be
beneficial for cardom metabolic
protection potentially helping to
improve blood pressure cholesterol and
blood sugars note it's specified that
these are food guidelines not supplement
guidelines though really they're more
like beverage guidelines as tea green or
black
would be by far the easiest way to reach
those levels though there are also
certainly some in a variety of berries
and cocoa however there is an enzyme
called polyphenol oxidase that can break
down polyphenols like flavonols that's
what causes certain fruits and
vegetables to Brown when you cut into
them like bananas and potatoes why would
a plant do that to itself apparently as
a defense mechanism part of the plant's
own immune system when when exposed to
oxygen polyphenol oxidase can oxidize
polyphenols into breakdown products with
antimicrobial activity so when a banana
gets bruised or you cut open an avocado
the polyphenol oxidase can start
oxidizing polyphenols into defensive
compounds that can glomp together and
form a brown compound called melanin the
same class of compounds that darkens the
skin of a banana darkens our skin
too okay no problem we can just not eat
Brown bananas as that's Visual Evidence
that many of the polyphenols have been
lost but what if you mixed that banana
which you know is filled with a
polyphenol oxidase enzyme into a
smoothie with polyphenol rich foods like
berries or cocoa might you end up with
less nutrition big chocolate funded
researchers sought to find out they put
about a half a cup of Coco's worth of
cocoa flavanols into a smoothie
containing banana compared to the same
amount in a berry smoothie with no
bananas here's a measure of how many the
chocolate flavanols made it into the
bloodstream within hours of drinking the
chocy berry smoothie compared to the
same amount of cocoa blended into a
banana smoothie it's almost as if you
hardly put any cocoa in there at all
presumably because the banana enzymes
chopped up all the chocolate goodies
let's not presume though
they Blended up the chocy banana
smoothie again banana almond milk and
Coco flavanol and then just measured the
amount of flavanol as to smooth the SAT
for an hour check it out the cocoa
flavanols plummeted more than a 90% drop
a halflife of like 10 minutes so every
10 minutes or so the levels drop in half
how do they know for sure it was the
polyphenol oxidase enzyme because when
they added specific enzyme blockers they
block the effect
okay no problem if you're adding bananas
to your smoothies Can you just chug it
quickly before the enzyme does its job
and presumably the enzyme will be
deactivated when it hit the Acid Bath of
the stomach but let's not presume you
don't know until you put it to the test
I love that the researchers did all
these extra steps this time they made
study participants alternate sips
between a straight banana almond milk
smoothie and like chocolate milk Coco
Flav plus almond milk so there was no
premixing in the blender between the
banana enzyme and the flavonol just
mixing in the stomach here's how many
cocoa flavonols make it into your
bloodstream when sipping the chocolate
milk alone mixed in the stomach with
banana and you get this 37% Less in your
bloodstream which shows that the banana
enzyme can still do some polyphenol
damage in the stomach and yes in
simulated stomach acid conditions the
polyphenol oxidates enzyme is is indeed
down but not out so yeah if you drink a
smoothie with banana in it it's better
to not let it sit around but even if you
drink it immediately you may still get
less polyphenols in your system than if
you would have skipped the banana but
banana makes smoothie so rich and creamy
anything we can add to the Smoothie to
counter the banana enzymes effects
that's exactly what I'll cover
next for